[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is software
engineering radio with felina today
with me on the show is ken newent clark
he is a data engineer at the critical
path
institute in tucson arizona working on
the rare
diseases initiative ken has a bachelor's
degree in english literature and started
to work as a programmer right after
college
first learning visual basic on windows
3.1
after working in several industry jobs
ken spent 13 years at the planned
genomics project in cold spring harvard
laboratory
in 2014 he joined dr borney hurwitz at
the university of arizona
he completed a master's degree in
biosystems engineering in 2019
and ken has just published his first
book tiny python projects in 2020
and ken's book is going to be the topic
of the show today
welcome to the show ken oh thank you so
much philly i very much appreciate you
having me here
great so the first thing of course i'm
very curious about
is why a book on python there are so
many programming languages out there
why do you think python is the best
choice to learn programming
in 2020 well it the the book really grew
out of trying to teach
biologists some basic programming skills
at the university of arizona
and and this really goes back to my
experience at cold spring harbor working
with dr lincoln stein
he started a programming course for
biologists and at the time
he started late 90s and early 2000s he
was teaching in pearl
and which was exactly actually why i
went to work for him so
it was really about trying to get some
sort of a programming language into the
hands
of biologists so that they could learn
how to process the data that they were
using
and bonnie and i met in the lab of
lincoln hurwitz
i'm sorry bonnie and i met in dr dr
lincoln stein's lab
and and so when we came to the
university of arizona and started
uh the herwitz lab we also wanted to
have that same kind of a class to teach
biologists
uh how to do some basic programming and
so we started off with pearl
you know 2015 and even in 2015 pearl was
really on
on the downside as far as its popularity
in
in our field and python was really
rising especially with the ascendancy of
things like machine learning
and numpy and so many great modules so
after a year or so of teaching pearl i
convinced
dr hurwitz that we should switch over to
teaching python just because it's so
so widely used in scientific computing
and
and it has so much to offer for the
students and
and so we just kind of converted our
materials the same kinds of examples
over into python and then i just kept
writing more and more examples so
in the classroom i kept trying to find
examples that i thought
really helped to teach the language and
and that's where this material came from
i'm not necessarily convinced that
python is
the best language to to learn maybe as a
beginner i think it has a lot of
advantages but specifically we were
trying to teach
some basic programming to you know
scientific computing skills
to undergraduates and graduate students
so to summarize i think what you said is
python is very popular language and it
also has
very good properties because it's meant
for
data science for machine learning for
scientific computing and not just python
itself but the libraries and the
ecosystem around it
make it very good for data sciency
type of applications is that right i
would definitely agree with all of that
yes
and you also mentioned that python has
some advantages
so i want to dive into that a little bit
deeper what do you think are some of the
language features that python has that
makes it so good for novice programmer
well you know they're making the
transition from perl
say to python which i did myself too i
just kind of
made myself become a python programmer
and
pearl uses the sigils in front of
variables so you know a dollar sign or
an at
sign a percent sign to to to help
identify the different types of
variables that you're working with
and i think a lot of people find that
kind of syntax very confusing
i kind of relate it to like hungarian
notation that i learned in maybe the
late 90s where you put like
str in front of a variable name to help
you remember that that's a string or
i in front of the you know at the
beginning like i numb
to remind you that that's an integer and
so i think it's it's
to me that was useful in pearl but i
think a lot of people found it confusing
some people do like braces to
delineate blocks but python uses white
space and so
some people find the lack of braces and
the forcing of
of indentation to make python more
readable
i think that's it probably is i still
see students produce
very very unreadable code uh even with
those those uh
white space requirements but more than
anything i really think the repel
the reevaluate print loop that python
offers is is a fantastic
learning tool so it's something i really
encourage
uh in class that when when we're trying
to understand
like how to pop an element off a list
we open up python we just type python3
and then we have this reply then we
create a list
and then we're able to to look at that
list
to say well show me the list and it
shows this visual representation of
something that looks like a list and
then we can say you know pop a member
off
and then we see that the list is now
shorter i think that that kind of an
interactive tool
is really really useful for teaching
students
beyond those things there are lots of
other tools like
the tools that there are for formatting
code like
ypf and black linting tools like flake 8
and pylint which i also cover in the
book
i think those can really help a person
figure out what's going wrong with their
code or just
find ways to improve it and and really
i think the biggest thing that it's
maybe not a language feature but there
is this huge community
around python and which includes a lot
of documentation
and just places to go where you can just
google for you know like
uh i just teach the students like you
know python
ad element to a list i mean you just
google for that you're gonna find
dozens and dozens of examples and
answers from everywhere from reddit to
stack overflow there's so many books
it's
those things i think just the community
around python also make it
a very strong language and and make it
easier to learn because there are
places and people to go to when you get
stuck yeah i totally are i think the
community of python is definitely
something that's not necessarily the
language itself but that makes
python a really nice language for
learners
and also in either raffle and
the fact that blocks are delineated by
spaces and
or tabs instead of brackets i think also
that's a nice thing
that helps novices learn to like program
in a structured way because it forces
them
to do things in a certain way so those
are some of the things that
that are really nice for beginners not
all of our audience of course
are beginners in python so i'm also
curious to hear what you think are some
of the
more advanced very exciting python
language features or
it doesn't have to be a language feature
it can also again be broader in terms of
the environment of the or the community
what are some of the exciting things for
more advanced programmers to get out of
python
i think the the thing that i've been
most excited about
recently and i think it started in
python 36 was the
edition of type hinting and so i saw uh
i think it was a c plus plus programmer
you know
had a tweet like the the feeling in the
c plus plus community is like wouldn't
our code be a lot cleaner if we could
get rid of all these type annotations
and then and then the it's kind of the
opposite in the python community i think
is this like wouldn't our code be a lot
cleaner if we could add all these type
annotations
and i actually really uh i've become
more enamored of strictly typed
languages
over the last couple of years and i
actually have been really using the type
hinting a lot more
i don't introduce it and type in tiny
python projects until the very last
chapter
as kind of a like here's where you could
go from here and here's some of the
things that you would get
as benefits to using this new feature
but
it's that combined with things like data
classes
and and these structures called name
tuples that act more like this uh
destruct in other languages you can
essentially create
new types in in python and then instead
of passing around like say
a string you could say i'm passing in a
phone number or
you know a social security number if
you're programming the internet in the
united states maybe but
and so it allows you to more accurately
describe
the things that you're dealing with and
and i think that
that has really made my python code a
lot more
interesting and and easier to check with
tools like my
pie which i i really find to be quite a
good tool
i i was really influenced by my journey
through
probably about 15 16 years of being a
pearl programmer
really enamored of larry wall and his
approach to
pearl he really felt like there should
be kind of a baby pearl that you could
learn
that would work and that you could be
productive in and then as you got
better with the language you could start
using things that were fancier and maybe
more powerful
and i think python really lends itself
to that as well so you don't need to
start programming with
with type annotations but after you get
to that point where you're like oh
you know i made this mistake in my code
if only there would have been a way for
me to have caught that
as you know without it being a runtime
exception something that blows up when
the program's running
and i think that when you can show
someone like oh if we can describe our
code this way
and then i and then like in the book i
say okay let me introduce this error
like
i type i put quotes around true so it's
actually a string instead of a boolean
type
and if i run this tool it'll actually
see that i made that mistake and that's
you know
that's a pretty easy mistake to make and
so i think that
that sort of uh this this idea of like
gradually typing your
code which is also something that they
really brought into the idea of pearl
six which is i think now called raku
that everything starts off as an any
type but as you
need you can start describing things
more more clearly like this is an end or
this is a string
and so i think that those are things
that could really take
someone's maybe intermediate level
python to
a whole other level if you start
introducing types
and and really trying to explore tools
like my pi and see
what it can do to improve your the
reliability of your code
yeah i think that's a great addition
people of course think of python as a
dynamically typed language which it is
but these optional typing features that
are new in python that people might not
be aware
of in need can help you find errors
more easily i'm really interesting or
interested also to hear like a more
concrete example you mentioned something
like
social security numbers but you also
said that using types have has made your
coding
more interesting so could you give an
example of where adding types
really added something to the code base
well
there's there was actually it was the
module that i just released last week
it's it's an idea i've been exploring is
something i have to do
so much is parsing csv
files parsing you know the export from
an excel spreadsheet
and especially in this one project that
i'm i just left
there was essentially a value
that you know some floating point value
in each record
and a lot of the data i get is really
really messy and there maybe that is
encoded as some string to show that the
value is missing
and or maybe it's just it was encoded in
a way that can't be converted to a
floating point value
and so i kept having to solve the same
problem with each different data set and
they all look different because i was
getting data from
you know a dozen different places and uh
so i was
trying to parse through each record and
parse this and convert this floating
point value and then
you know if i was able to create this
idea of a record this this this uh
this data point then i could continue
forward with loading that into a
database or
you know another csv file and i came up
with a way of
describing what a record should look
like
out of this out of this any file
and i describe it with a type that i
annotate
use and so it is a it is a class that
i'm using
and i really i make a point in the in
the book that i pretty much avoid
personally working and teaching object
oriented programming style but
in this instance i am creating a class
based on a named tuple
which has this also side effect of
giving me this read-only uh
this immutable data structure and i can
describe
in the class that you know this thing
has some sort of a
variable name that is a string and but
it also has a value that is a float
and i'm able to pass this into uh this
this module that i created
that does the automatic that does the
conversions for me and if it's able to
create that
kind of a record that kind of a shape
then it returns it to me
and if it's unable to do that then it it
could throw an exception or it could
do something else but um it was it
allowed me to
describe what i wanted at a higher level
and solve a problem at a more abstract
level because i was able to describe it
using
types rather than writing the same code
for
every single csv file that i'm trying to
parse
i hope that's a good example yeah i
think that's a great example
i would like to hear a little bit more
detail because you also said that you
use
named tuples and that gave you an
immutable data structure so not
everyone in the audience might exactly
understand everything that you said
there so
could you explain in a little bit more
depth what names tuples are in python
and how they give you immutability yeah
this is
i find this really fascinating it's one
of my one definitely one of my favorite
aspects of the language that i've been
using over the last couple years
so i'm very much influenced by my
experience
programming or trying to program in
haskell i'll be honest i've never
actually been productive in haskell
but i keep reading about it i find it a
fascinating language
there is a dialect of haskell called elm
that i've used on a couple projects to
create
web user interfaces so essentially it's
it's a a subset of haskell that
that compiles to javascript which i find
just fascinating and so that's a purely
functional programming language that
i've been able to really wrap my head
around and become
uh familiar with and and one of the
hallmarks of languages like that is that
you essentially don't have variables you
have symbols
that are attached to you know functions
or data structures
but you're not allowed to change these
data structures
you have to create new data structures
from old data structures
and when i first heard this um because i
mean
going again going back i do not have a
computer science background i you know
i've come from english literature and
music so i'm completely self-taught and
so
you know the idea that a variable is by
definite definition not
variable i was like well then how do you
get anything done in a language like
this you know
and um and and but then i started to see
over and over again as i was
forced into a language where you're not
allowed to mutate
any values that you just keep creating
new structures that's like oh
i i see advantages to this kind of a
programming approach
and also just where everything is just a
function
they're just there are no objects
there's no global state
there you there's no global uh you know
in you know integer value that you can
increment
and stuff like that you're just like all
of a sudden forced to encapsulate
everything and
and there's a lot of rigor to the
language and at first that's really
really difficult and very constraining
but then after a while i started to see
how much the compiler was able to help
me
and and of keep me from making certain
kinds of mistakes that i was
always making and so i wanted to kind of
cargo cult those ideas
into python and so in python we have
lists
so strings oddly are immutable uh you
can't like change
a letter in a string uh you have to set
the the variable equal to an entirely
new string value
but lists are not lists are completely
mutable you can mutate any part of a
string
uh reverse it and all that kind of stuff
right there in place
and so a tuple in python is an immutable
list
so it's essentially a list and you have
list access just the way you have
uh normally but you can't say pop
an element out of a tuple you can't
reorder the elements you can't change an
element in place
and so a named tuple allows you to use
that immutable data structure but assign
names to the slots instead of like
getting at the zeroth element in the
first element you can say the zeroth
element is the name and the second
element
is you know the person's age and things
like that so you start getting this
this data access that really looks like
an object because it's going to be like
you know
tuple dot name without the parentheses
because it's not a method call it's it's
a field in
in that data structure and then
so name tuples give you essentially a
data structure
that looks like an object that has a
little bit i think nicer syntax for
accessing the elements than a dictionary
but then when you add type hinting on
top of that
you get an immutable object-like data
structure
that you can now pass around and you you
have this guarantee
from python itself that no part of that
object is going to be mutated
uh accidentally by your code and an an
example of when i would use that for
instance is i always represent the
arguments to
my program as an args data structure
and the arguments are like those are set
in stone
those came from the user at run time and
i don't want
at any point my code to accidentally
modify
some parameter that was given at runtime
so when i represent that as a named
tuple i get that guarantee in my code
and i just can
kind of put that idea to rest i know
that's not going to happen that
that data structure is not going to be
accidentally mutated anywhere in my code
that's a lot but hopefully does that
does that makes i hope i explained that
well
yeah i think so so if i may summarize
what i think you're saying is that
some of the concepts of object
orientation and some of the concepts
of functional programming are are useful
and new features in python allow you to
make use of some of these
more functional style properties like
immutability
and some of the more oo like features
like typing
to create a language that sort of has it
all that has the
dynamic feel of pearl if you need it but
that also can help you make less
mistakes
by giving you types and giving you
immutability where it makes sense
is that sort of a summary of what you
said yeah i would
yeah that's very good thanks then
now i want to move on to the topic of
the show i think we convinced everyone
now that python is a great language
that's very versatile
so you decided to write a book on
teaching people that have no prior
programming experience python
and i was wondering what is the gap
you're feeling because there are many
books already out there
to teach people programming or to teach
people python what is the specific
aim of your book why do you think an
extra book was still needed
i think from my own experience of
learning
programming languages and i've i've you
know just keep learning them
and and i i find this the field
fascinating
um one of the things that i stumble with
when i'm trying to learn a language is
just seeing a large enough example
of a program a full working program so
often i'll be like
like i remember when i was first
learning haskell and it was just
trying to show me like how a function
works
and and finally i wrap my head around
that and i'm like okay great
now how would i use this in a larger
context like how would i write
a program that i can run that that reads
in something like a list and then does
this thing that you were showing me
about lists in pascal
how can i do that and i just was stuck
i'm like well
how do i how do i write the program
right i just i want more of context and
so
that was i think the first thing i just
felt like so many programming books
show you just a little bit of code like
here's here's a list
but like how do you create a list in
when you in
in a program uh and so i wanted to show
that's like the second
or third you know uh element in in the
book
is it's called going on a picnic and so
you get these
you get some command line arguments and
they're a list and if you get one you're
supposed to show it like this and if you
get two you show it like this other
thing
and and so i just felt like showing
people more context
would be useful for learning python for
learning any language
but really i think the the secret thing
that i'm trying to sneak in
and it's maybe not too secret is testing
i think that
especially beginners are not taught
testing i think this
is and and i know i wasn't at all you
know like you mentioned in the intro i
learned visual
basic back in like 96 and
i would say the first five ten years of
my programming
experience no one ever used test i
worked in a bunch of industry jobs i
worked you know
delivering commercial software and there
were no tests
in sight testing just wasn't done and
then finally i started coming across
testing
i was reading and and and i would see
when i would compile
programs and i would see i'm supposed to
run make tests and then you know
10 minutes later it's done with this
test suite and finally i was like what's
going on there with testing
and i started looking into it i'm like
oh if i started testing my software it
would be better
and then when i started teaching i
didn't have test at first i was just
kind of doing it the way that i had
always been taught like here we're going
to write a program we're just going to
look at it and
if it looks like it ran okay then great
thumbs up you did great job
and then i found that if i introduce
testing and i say okay now we we have
this thing over here that's going to run
your program
and tell you precisely is it right or
wrong and if it's wrong it's going to
tell you exactly what's wrong
i found that actually was really useful
i think that
testing seems like it's often going to
be saved until later until you're some
sort of an advanced programmer
and then you'll learn it or like maybe
when you go to your first job in
industry you'll learn it
and i think that's exactly the wrong way
to approach it i think that we
you know i work with kids to help them
learn bicycles
you never put a kid on a bicycle without
a helmet i mean it's just
i mean when i was growing up in the 70s
we didn't have car seats or helmets but
but we know better now we use helmets
and so
there's no reason why not to teach
someone programming
like from the beginning hey you can test
your program
and and and you can make sure that it
actually does what you think it does
and i think that that's probably the the
biggest reason why i wanted to write
this book is to
give example after example of what it
means to write a program
against a test suite and when you're
done you actually know that it works
for some idea of some specification
i really like this bicycle helmet
example even though i live in a country
where no one wears a helmet if they bike
i i do get it so it makes sense to have
built-in safety however testing is also
hard and even professional programmers
with decades of experience
still struggle to come up with the right
tests and often
they think their code is correct but
then once it's running
it turns out that they missed some sort
of edge case
so how do you concretely teach people to
test
if they're not really advanced
programmers because some some part of
testing
just comes with experience like knowing
oh i have to test
an empty input i have to test a really
large input
these are things that also sort of come
from having been
bit in the ass by errors many times how
do you explain the value of testing
to norfolk your first point is is
exactly true i
i just left a project that had been
around for a year or so
mostly python written by some pretty
experienced
developers not a test in site not a
single test and so
i was actually brought in to help create
tests and and one of the first things i
did was i would just
run a program with no arguments
expecting to see like some sort of a
usage or something like that in the test
i mean the program actually just charged
ahead with bad input
just created exceptions and stack traces
and i'm like
yeah this is a problem you really need
to practice you know you need to
run your program if it expects a file
you should give it something that's not
a file
and and make sure that it detects those
things and i
it is difficult to teach people
especially beginners
testing and so you know my goal
and and i've used this this book in a
class a couple times now that i've
taught
and you know again that's that's where
this material came from
mostly what i'm hoping that you'll get
by the end of the book
is that tests can be written i try to
get the user i try to get the reader to
write
unit tests the integration tests are
quite a bit more difficult because you
kind of have to understand like the
command line a little bit
and that's what i'm really providing
especially up front are these
integration tests so
test that will so you know to start off
you're supposed to create hello world
and it's supposed to be called hello.py
and so the first test is that you
created a file called
hello.py right and then uh and then it
runs the
the program and with like it's supposed
to say hello
uh universe instead of hello world and
it verifies that it does that
and i think just example after example
getting the user
getting the reader to to to run that
test suite to
look at the test output um i hope that
after seeing
what is like 22 examples of of that
that they'll they'll kind of see the
utility of this and i
really stress that you know around
chapter five we start getting into file
handling
and i say okay your program should
expect a file that it's going to read
just so you know the test suite is going
to give you something that's just
garbage
it's going to say it's going to give you
a non-existent file
for that value and so i'm trying to
teach you
defensive programming in the same way i
say okay this this parameter
to the program is going to be an integer
by the way the test suite is going to
give you a string for that
and your your program is going to be
responsible for detecting
that that's not an integer value and and
you know and
throughout the book i'll say okay let's
just peek under the hood what's going on
in this test program
and we start looking at a bit of the
code and i say do you see here
how i'm creating this is the name of
your program and this is the name of
this parameter and here i'm passing a
good value
and here i'm passing a bad value and
when i pass a bad value i expect that
the program
should return for instance a non-zero
exit value
i've tried to teach you know the the
idea of a well-behaved
program that should properly report its
errors
to the greater operating system and so
and and you know even working on this
project that i just left where you know
again
written by professional software
developers with perhaps decades of
experience
trying to introduce the tests and just
like i
literally spent like a month or six
weeks just like saying
here's an example of a test here here's
how we test here's what we should be
doing
and finally tests started to be written
just as i was leaving the project and so
it is an enormously difficult thing to
get across eve
from the beginner to the experienced
person but
i think that if you keep showing
examples of
how this leads to better more reliable
code
it really starts to show its utility
especially
with the ideas of refactoring which is
you know
something i really talk about in the
book a lot because i don't just find
one example one way to solve something
uh
there's one this this uh silly exercise
called apples and bananas
as a children's song and i like to eat
eat
eat apples and bananas and then you
start saying i like to ight
height i presume benign eyes and things
like that and so it's just teaching
children uh
these kind of vowel sounds and so the
idea in this is that you're supposed to
replace all the vowels with one vowel so
uh given any input phrase and so i show
like eight different ways to do that
and the whole point of the test suite is
that i can write
a simple uh solution that works and
passes the test suite
and then i can say okay i have freedom
now to
explore and find other ways in the
language that i can do the same thing
and i can always come back to the test
suite
and verify that my program still does
what it's supposed to do and it's
instantaneous and painless to just
say pi test and it just runs it and
there's just no effort at all required
because i as the author have provided
the test suite
but i hope that by the end of the of the
of the book
that you realize wow there really is a
lot more freedom
by having this strict uh test in place
that really verifies that my program
does exactly what i think it does
so in summary what i think you said is
you have to show novices
lots of examples lots of example test
code this is how test code looks like
so so they get the hang of it and also
show
specific situations in which tests
really add value for example
if you're refactoring if you're
modifying your code then you can rely
you can trust your tests to
help you understand if the code is still
working as intended so
giving examples and giving example
scenarios
where tests are really valuable that's
the way to get even beginners
to experience testing yes then there's
more in your book also because the
subtitle of your book
is learn coding and testing with puzzles
and games so i want to ask you many
things about all of the individual parts
of that so testing i think
we've covered encoding we've covered
also but then there's still
puzzles and games so what what are
puzzles what type of puzzles does the
book cover
it's a lot of them are so you know
in trying to create a program that you
can teach something from
there you know i was trying to get
across maybe three or four maybe five
skills in any one
exercise and i definitely wanted the
programs to be
a hundred lines or fewer probably a lot
of the programs especially in the early
part are
70 lines or fewer and and that's pretty
generous too because i'm using a a
formatter that is you know pretty
vertical as far as the way it
distributes code so
so i had to choose examples that were
really simple enough that they i could
fit into that few lines of a code
and and i also just i wanted the
cognitive load to be
lower so i didn't want to teach
something really complex like the the
goal of the
of the proj of the program and also
the programming thing that we're the
programming concepts that we're trying
to learn are also
really complex so i was trying to keep
things really simple
um i for instance really like the ideas
of cryptography
uh and and chapter four introduces this
idea of it's called jump to five so
given a string
find all the numbers in the string and
then encode the numbers
by using this algorithm called jump to
five so if you look at a standard keypad
on a telephone the one would jump to
five to become a nine
and the two would jump the five to
become an eight and the five and the
zero then swap places with each other
and so that right there i feel like
there's a lot of interesting things to
to to piece out like how okay how do you
iterate over
every character in a string how do you
identify something that
is a number given a number how do you
change it to something else
given something that's not a number how
do you just skip over it so i think
there's a
you know that's a a kind of puzzle it's
also a kind of encryption
and and a way of encoding text
like a secret kind of and i feel like
that's kind of interesting
uh it also by the way comes from like a
television show called the wire
which was pretty popular in the united
states a few years back and
and so it has like there's there's an
interesting backstory i think to it
so like that's a simple little puzzle i
think
that makes for an interesting uh chapter
that i could write
you know another one's not really a
puzzle but it's like an insult generator
i think
and and i really wanted to to um i
wanted the book to be playful in fact my
original title was playful python
i wanted the book to just be interesting
and fun and so
there's an insult generator and and i'm
also targeting
really you know my oldest is 16 and he
won't read my book but
he might one day and uh but that's the
age that i was really i was hoping
maybe even a middle schooler might find
it funny and interesting enough but
probably not i have used this at the at
the university level and
and i think that these are simple enough
to understand the idea of what the
program is supposed to do
but still interesting enough to make you
want to finish it so
it's you know the the the the the insult
generator
uses a bunch of shakespearean adjectives
and nouns in it
and uh and it teaches you about
randomness and setting random seeds and
taking random samples and then putting
strings together and iterating over
things and doing things a certain number
of times
so there's a lot of things that you can
teach in that silly example that doesn't
do anything useful in the world
but what you end up with is something
that you can now sit there and you know
and
hurl insults at your sister or something
and and that's funny
to you know to an extent maybe i think
it's a little funny
uh and so i'm just trying to keep with
simple things like
you know mad libs do you have mad libs
in in your part of the world
yeah okay so you know um that is an
example where
you could talk about regular expressions
and so and i think
and that's a really common thing that
most people have encountered that idea
and so there's not a lot to teach there
and then tic-tac-toe is where i end and
i know that's uh
not a groundbreaking uh to do
tic-tac-toe but i think that i
show for instance a way to test like
if you're going to create a tic-tac-toe
game how do you ensure that it works
correctly
and and for a game that is actually
interactive where you have two players
who are who are
choosing things that you you know you
can't test
the whole game maybe like that in its
interactive state but you can break it
down into
units into functions that can be tested
so you know that with this part of the
program
is run i know it's going to run
correctly so those are the kind of games
and puzzles that i was
trying to target ever dreamt of building
an app that impacts the daily lives of
hundreds of thousands of people
well now's your chance monday.com is a
work os
that helps teams work together they
launched the monday apps challenge to
bring developers around the world
together to build apps and they're
giving away 180 000
in prizes including three teslas check
it out at monday.com
sc radio and start building now that's
monday.com
se radio
i think you probably already answered my
next questions i was going to ask you
what is it about puzzles and what is it
about games that
make them really good for teaching and i
i think you answer that by saying that
puzzles and games are fun and
interesting and
there they are a way to get people
interested in coding and also to convey
what the things are that coding can do
for you but i'm still also wondering
about downsides so are there any
downsides about
using games as a context
well i definitely saw you know i follow
a lot of things on reddit and
and somebody was with made this exact
comment about like you know i'm sick of
seeing
everything about learning python being
about games
and you know i think specifically they
were sharing some idea of like a class
um you know for teaching object-oriented
stuff in python that was like a player
and uh you know like a player maybe
maybe like some sort of a first person
shooter game
and and they were like can we please get
away from every example being about
games
and i don't actually play games like
that i've never been enamored of
computer
games and doom and uh all those kinds of
things uh
so i guess i was just thinking about
like games that you could just like draw
on a piece of paper
or that you would just kind of do in the
car
and so yeah i mean not everyone's
interested in games
yeah i was all in some of my examples
that didn't make it into the book are
like uh from board games like
yahtzee uh which is a dice game or
scrabble
which is a tile based game with letters
i'm personally interested in those kinds
of
of algorithms like you know given seven
tiles
and one other tile what are all the
possible words that i could spell
that was my scrabble game to me that's
very interesting it may not be
interesting to someone else and so
you know i i recognize that do you think
creating those games so not necessarily
the games per se but the process of
creating games and puzzles
is that a good representation of what a
programming career is about
oh certainly not yeah i mean but
honestly
honestly what i've done so much of my
career would probably just be
very boring to somebody you know to
teach from the beginning i mean
unfortunately a lot of what i've done is
like
cleaning up input data files uh so i get
again going back to like a comma
separated values uh input file you know
or an excel spreadsheet
that i get from a researcher or i
download
as you know the supplement to a paper
and i need to incorporate this data into
some database i have and so you know
like that right there is probably been
50 of my career is building databases
and loading them
and that's fairly advanced i mean
there's there's and actually that's a
book that i want to write
one day and uh but i don't think that
you know you can
i don't i certainly don't think i could
take a teenager and convince them that
this was really interesting and that you
could make
a really cool career out of cleaning
data sets
for scientists but it's a really
important part of the process of you
know if we're going to move knowledge
forward
we need to have an accurate
representation of it we need to collate
it
and aggregate it and analyze it and so
um no it means certainly gaming and
these kinds of puzzles
are not representative of really what
i've done but there are elements
to each program that carry over directly
into things that i do every day
and when i was using these examples for
my class
i would teach a chapter we would work
over on a chapter on tuesday
and then on the thursday class it would
be applying that idea
to something in genomics uh something in
our field
and then we would just spend the whole
class on thursday talking about
like that more applied example and
i i think that the the step from these
simple games
to things that you would actually do in
the real world i try to make at the end
of the chapter is kind of like a little
going further idea
and i i try to make a hint at like how
you could use this
in a larger context in a more realistic
context
and maybe i didn't always you know
really convey that as well as i should
but
i i think that's my answer yeah i
totally think the answer makes sense
like you want to emphasize the cool
parts of programming any interesting
parts of programming and sort of
initially step over to things that might
be
boring or repetitive yeah i was not sure
we don't always do that right if you
teach your teenager to do some cooking
there are also boring parts you have to
wash your hands you have to
wait for water to boil not everything
can be
exciting all the time so so there
probably is some sort of balance where
we
want to show them some boring parts
maybe you could also say that
focusing on the testing and focusing on
the correctness sort of is also
somewhat boring it's probably less fun
than creating something yourself but
there you
you you air on the side of caution
you're like this is so important
so we definitely want to show how to
test code so i just just
like an interesting brainstorm question
how much of the boring stuff
do we want to show them to give them a
sense of what programming is
and how much cool stuff do we want to
give to also lure them
in so i'd say i think you just have to
keep
mixing the two together uh and layering
them um you know a spoonful of sugar
helps the medicine go down right so
and and and i bring in the testing in
the very very first example like okay
we're going to write hello world
here's the test to make sure that it
writes that we actually print hello
world and you can't miss
a single space or a comma any piece of
punctuation it has to be
perfect and and that push to perfection
yeah that's boring it's like oh come on
didn't i get it close enough
well no i mean you know that's it's
close is not good enough most of the
time at least you know when we when
we're writing computer programs
and it might be in cooking and i was
working actually with my youngest this
weekend in the kitchen i was trying to
get him to
help him make a cake and and i'd set out
two sticks of butter
and he was gonna throw you know one was
for the icing and one was for the cake
and he was about to throw both of them
into the cake and i was like wait
stop i was like you need to read the
directions he's like i did read the
directions this says to add the butter
i'm like how much butter he's like it
doesn't say i'm like it does
say i swear to wood says add one stick
of butter
and so yeah i mean you know on the and
so like after i had
i admonished him a couple times like he
was really getting down my wife was like
hey
you're being a little hard on him you
know he's just gonna leave i'm like
you're right
i need to keep him focused on the fact
that he's going to have a chocolate cake
at the end of this
exercise and he did he made it and we
got past you know a couple rough things
but you know at the end i'm like okay
you got to watch those pots and and i
just laughed
like you're the cook like this part of
cooking
um so yeah i mean you you have to teach
those
those i mean it's not that hard of a
lesson but you know
your program should be correct i mean it
should
and we have ways of verifying that
programs are correct
and it's not that burdensome to make
sure that that we've actually
written it correctly and i think
specifically working in the field of
scientific computing
we have a utter complete crisis
of reproducibility and i think
what i've seen since i i came to
university of arizona in 2014
and uh and really got to work like
really in academic research computing
and really working more with graduate
students undergrads and post-docs
and seeing how much of the burden of
science
falls on them the pi's come up with the
ideas for the experiments and then it's
these
students jobs or these young
professionals
jobs to execute these these experiments
and to analyze these data sets
and often they're producing data sets
that are
quite large and extensive and they need
help
computing help to analyze them and the
pis don't have that and everyone just
seems to assume that people are going to
just find out they're going to figure
out on their own
how to write programs and that the these
programs are actually going to be
reproducible so that when they're
released as the supplement or the github
repository for
for for uh for paper that other people
are going to be able to download and use
these programs and
like most of the time they're not
they're really
horribly written and they barely work
for the person who wrote them
and they're not going to work at all in
a different computing environment
and so you know just from a larger
standpoint of what i'm trying to do in
the world i want to make
computing reproducible and if you're
going to work
in a dynamically uh somewhat loosely
typed language like python
you're going to have to write tests if
you're going to if you choose to work in
a stricter language
testing may be less important it's still
going to be important
um you know especially just like given
this input file
if i run my program do i get this output
file i mean you need to verify these
things
and so those were some of the things
that i was trying to do with
like why is this important and yes we're
trying to create
cool things but along the way they have
to be right
yeah i think this balance it's is even
true for professional programmers
it's always nice to create things and
then you should
you get excited and you get into the
flow of programming you have to tell
yourself
well wait wait i need to add some tests
or if everything is done
maybe i should be a responsible person
and refactor this code so it's more
readable
there's always this tension between
creating things and then
cleaning up after yourselves in
programming but also
in other areas so i i guess some of the
tension there is also just some
decisions you made for the book
well actually if i could if i could
follow up on that sure
i think that you know obviously i was
writing this book and then like putting
my name on this
and so i was really trying to
internalize these ideas and really
trying to explore
what is test driven development so of
course that that phrase comes from
i think it's 2002 book by kent beck
and the basic pedagogy is you write
you you have some feature that your
program should do and so you write a
test
that verifies that your that your
software does not do that thing
you run this test you see it fails
that's the first step
and then you go right the function that
or the or you implement the feature
that fulfills that test and then you run
the test suite and now you see
it does hopefully pass your test suite
it's kind of the same thing like my wife
and i joke that like
you know once we had children we had to
start eating better
right like we kind of ate a lot of you
know store-bought
junk and and i didn't really focus on a
lot of fresh vegetables and then
all of a sudden you're this model for
these these young people
and you want them to grow up eating well
and having good habits so you have to
model these things and so
you know i started really pushing these
ideas on myself like okay
i need to write this function and and
really it has come to dominate
the way that i write especially in
python is that i write the test
first i think of the function that i
want
to exist and i first go write you know
test underscore function because i'm
using pi test so it runs all the
functions that start with test
underscore and i say okay
this this this putative function is
going to take
a list and it's going to return a string
so what happens when i give it an empty
list okay well i would expect to get
back
an empty string if i give it a list with
one element i expect to get back
this string you know so i actually write
down
examples so that i can see if i give it
this i'm going to get back this
and then i go write the function and
i've been surprised
i i how many times i misunderstood my
own ideas
and it was only by virtue of having
written that test that i
realized that i i didn't implement the
function correctly
and i've been programming for like 24
years i mean
and and i've done a master's degree and
i've learned you know a dozen different
languages
and so i think i'm a pretty capable
programmer and i still make
really really dumb mistakes all the time
and it's only by virtue of forcing
myself and really not even forcing i
really this is how i think now i
i can't write code without writing tests
and i think that is a is a has been a
sea
change in my mind so the idea that i
come in later and write the test is
completely backwards to me
the tests come first and then i write
the program that's
that that satisfies the test yeah that
makes a lot of sense i'm not just
curious like
was this a slow evolution in your
thinking
or was there more like this big bang
this horrible one bug
sort of like the the birth of your
children that you describe
was like okay from now on i really have
to do better is there is there a juicy
story here or was it just
slowly you realizing that that was the
way to do it it was really slowly
realizing it
it was you know i i try to pride myself
on not making the same mistake the big
same mistake twice in life but i make a
lot of the same small mistakes
over and over again and i did they were
so painful like they accrete in my life
and finally i'm like
why am i doing this stupid thing and so
you know it was really when i started
releasing software
on cpan in perl the comprehensive pearl
archive network and i was like i finally
came up with
an idea that i wanted to share with the
world and i was really really excited
about it and i'm pretty sure my first
release had no
tests and then i started looking around
like oh
no tests are a part of what this
community does like that's kind of an
expected step
that there should be this testing
component to to the software and there
was a
few different testing harnesses and
sweets and pearl and so
you know i just took the time to learn
them i started learning about
you know code coverage and i started
thinking well can i get 100 code
coverage you know like in this small
module that i've written and i just
really kept pushing myself like what can
i do with testing
and then and then i just but it was only
for stuff that i was releasing it wasn't
really for stuff that i was writing day
to day
and and i just kept realizing especially
as in
again modeling this behavior for
students and teaching this in the
classroom and trying to show the utility
of this
and then starting to to really try to
make myself do it more
i realized this is this is actually
really really good
and but the other the other big thing
and
and i anticipate you may ask like what
are the things about python that make it
not so great
for teaching and and so there are a lot
of mistakes that you can make in python
that um if you're not really really
aware of like how
a lot of computer sciency stuff works
you're just going to get a runtime
exception the program's just going to
blow up
and so when i work in stricter languages
like
elm or rust certain classes of bugs just
don't exist for me
because the program won't even compile
if i you know have made
have forgotten to handle some exception
case and
in python that's not the case that the
python code will just compile we talked
about tie pens
and they're really really awesome but
python itself completely ignores them
you have to use a separate tool to
analyze your your code to see if you're
using the type ends correctly
because if a function says it takes an
integer and then at runtime it gets a
string
python doesn't care it'll just keep
running and create a runtime exception
and so what i just found was that when i
started really
adopting this test driven idea
when i'm writing python code my python
code is
much much better and and so finally just
like
you know stop fighting it just do it the
right way
and and your programs just end up
working a lot better
so we've covered python now as a
language and i really like that you
already
you just thrown in some of the downsides
of python which in this was also
something i wanted to ask about
so let's step away from python as a
language
and let's move on to how do you actually
do
python if you're a beginner because of
course when we were learning to program
there wasn't something like an ide there
was an integrated development
environment you would typically type
code in a text editor like thing and
then run it on the command line
but programming has changed quite a lot
so
how do you tell novices to deal with
that do they
install an ide do you start with
something like an ide
so that it can run tests and then maybe
it can do refactoring
is that something you also bring into
the toolkit kit of novices
or do they first have to learn it sort
of like we learned it the old-school way
in the command line
what is your pick and why i definitely
think that uh
ides can be extremely helpful to to the
beginner
and and i and i i do teach the command
line
in this book and and for like a windows
programmer it
is going to really require installing
something like windows subsystem for
linux which
in and of itself is a barrier
and and there's like you know there's a
payoff in that the programs that we
create i think are really stripped down
i think that learning command line
programming
is really really in some ways an ideal
way to to talk about things like a
string
or a file or a number and and and to
really just
think about programming concepts but
there is a barrier
to getting a command line environment
and actually i
really you know uh our listeners won't
know this but
but you looked at some early text of the
book and you had a lot of really great
feedback and one of which was like
what if a person is on a computer and
they can't install
python and python is not installed like
what are they going to do
have you looked at something like
replied r-e-p-l-i-t which is a website
that provides basically an ide
in the browser and a command line
environment
for for running these programs and when
i looked at it my mind was blown i was
like
i had no idea this existed and i can
totally see the utility for this because
uh like one of the things that my wife
has done over over the over the years is
like work with a lot of non-profits
especially
libraries and in this small town in new
mexico where we were
the computers at the library were for a
lot of people the only computer that
they
had in their life and they would come in
to check their email
do their taxes watch videos whatever it
was
and you know i'm specifically thinking
about those kids that would sit down
had no computer at home it wouldn't be
able to install python
on those on the library computers and so
when when i saw that i was like
this is a total gateway drug to being
able to do these sorts of things
and so in in when i'm teaching in class
i recommend that students install
something like vs code which is a
microsoft
tool uh integrated development
environment uh or
some of the editors like sublime
and pycharm is also an ide but some like
an editor like sublime or textmate
really have a lot of features that are
almost like an ide
so i think there are a lot of tools that
would really help a person
to write code i stress a lot
about going into the repple and and
using the help
documentation there but ides can just
right there in context show you oh this
is a string and you know you type
the name of the variable dot and it will
start saying oh here are all the methods
that belong to that class and so
those are things that could really help
a beginner and so i think that there's a
multitude of tools that
a beginner would probably really benefit
from using from
web-based ideas to uh ones that would
you can install on your own
program i mean on your own computer but
there really is like
just installing python itself if it's
not already installed
and a lot of times it is but if it's not
already installed on a computer that
in and of itself is not a beginner task
uh
so that could be just that could be a
huge barrier
you know my kids their first programming
experience has been scratch
from mit the little the little cat and
so
you know and and they're not really even
typing that much but they're being
introduced the ideas and variables and
and and loops and things like that and
so
i think that there are for more things
that we could do to make it easier for p
for beginners to learn
it's certainly not easy and in the first
couple weeks of class is really just
trying to get my students
there some sort of environment where
they can actually write and run
code i would say it takes about a month
before they really start feeling
comfortable with what they're doing
and do you think that changes over time
so with testing you take a strong stand
you say
testing you should learn it from the
beginning because it's important
so for an ide would you also say it's
important to use a very powerful tool
from the beginning because it matters or
would you say
as you are advancing as a programmer
your tools should also get more advanced
i definitely think that you should
be open to change you know and i say
that although i
i when i write code day-to-day i'm still
using vim
which i learned what in 1997. so you
know i haven't changed
i write code exactly the same way that
i've written it
over my entire career and i've had to
use ides like when i was you know
programming at delphi
and things like that but i always have
come back to the command line
when i'm teaching in class i use an ide
because i show i'm try again trying to
model what i think my students should be
doing i think that's
what's appropriate for them and and one
and like for instance vs code is is the
one that i've done all the videos with
right there in the window is a command
line so
you know you you have your you have your
file browser on the left you have
whatever
you know program you're working in on
the right and below that i have a little
editor i mean a little uh terminal
and i can just say okay go run the
program and run the test suite and then
there are the results right there
and so it i think it's a really useful
tool when i'm writing code for myself i
usually just have a couple terminal
windows open
so i think what you're saying but
correct me if i'm wrong here is that
your take is that ides are very valuable
for beginners
so you use them in teaching and you use
them in making videos for the book
but you yourself still prefer to program
on the command line
as a more advanced programmer i guess uh
and so much of it is muscle memory if
for your listeners who don't know vi
it has all these really cryptic key
combinations
um but um my my hands like never leave
the home keys right
my i just i'm able to do everything that
i want to do without the aid of a mouse
and just by typing and and and the
commands are just so
deeply embedded in my brain that i'm not
sure i could write
code as efficiently as i do uh if
if i were forced to use an ide all day
every day
they're really useful tools and i think
everyone should do whatever
is good for them whatever works for them
and this is what works for me and i
think i'll just keep doing it until i
die
i also want to cover us like a final
topic in this episode
the python ecosystem because all the way
in the beginning of the episode you said
what i really like about python is
everything it brings like libraries for
data science and for machine learning
so i want to like loop that back to
beginning
programmers do you think teaching just
vanilla python
is good for beginners or do you also
want to show them
from from the get-go hey python has this
super rich sea of modules and i think
there's one library oh yeah for example
in your book you do show
learners regular expressions so
apparently there are some of these
things that you think really
add some flavor to python what do you
think is
the best way show a bit show nothing
show many things does it depend on the
audience i i get
i think again this goes back to uh the
influence that i had
when i went over to say working in elm
and
i think that i just got so focused on on
like
what can i do with the string what can i
do with the list what can i do with
something like a dictionary
and i found that the more i focused on
understanding the fundamental data
structures that are
almost universal to pretty much any
language those kind of three things you
know strings
and and then numbers i guess and then
lists of dictionaries
i think really fundamentally
understanding those basic data
structures
is key to working in any
language i i do bring in regular
expressions i guess because they
they've been such a cornerstone of what
i have to do
especially when it comes to like
cleaning up data sets
there's so many problems that can be
described
with a regular expression and it's this
whole other thing that
i got introduced to really when a minute
went into pearl
and then especially when i went into
genomics because so much of what we do
is string manipulation and looking for
patterns and text
and so i really felt like that was
something that needed to be introduced i
almost never encounter certainly not a
novice programmer who's ever heard of
regular expressions and i think that
that's like a power tool
that you need to be made aware of really
quickly because
you'll be able to use that so many times
and another module i bring in is csv
for except for parsing comma separated
via files
but you know in talking to the editors
in creating this book with manning
they said you know there's only so far
you can take a person so on a scale of
of one to ten you know like one being a
novice and ten being like an expert
you're not going to take someone from a
one or two to a seven in the course of
one book
that's too great of a leap we really try
to shoot for like a movement of two or
three clicks
so you know from a beginner to
sort of around the cusp of an
intermediate maybe from an intermediate
to something more close to an expert
and so i wanted to start basically from
the beginning i
i know that if somebody's never seen a
function never heard of a loop or
variable
they would probably not be able to dive
straight into my book
but i think especially if you were
coming from a language where you already
basically knew these things and you just
wanted to know what the how they were
done in python
like you were moving over from
javascript or something i think that i
start at a good level
not too too basic and i think i move up
quickly enough where you would be kept
interested
and uh and so i i really do just want to
focus on
pi you know we start with python strings
and then we talk about how they're
similar to list and then we move into
lists and then we move into dictionaries
and then we move into file handling then
we talk about you know standard and
standard out standard error
but then we start talking about regular
expressions then we start talking about
like parsing files and making games and
randomness and
you know and so i think that there's a
lot of things i i
i guess i was just biased in what i
wanted to cover
there is a huge huge ecosystem of things
that python can do
and i just really wanted to focus on the
language itself and
and definitely um one of the early
reviewers he was a
he's a respected best-selling author
um and he also said well you're just
writing a vanilla python book you know
like why
why would somebody want another vanilla
python book and
and i just i guess you know
the secret thing the thing that i really
want to sneak in under the covers is the
testing
um so it you know python is a cool
language it has a rich ecosystem
but more than anything i want you to
leave the book
thinking no matter what language i'm
working in
i understand the basics of loops and
these basic data structures and i
understand that software needs to be
tested
and i understand you know a lot of the
skills that i
show in the book you could write python
tests for
a program that you write in any other
language because i'm just showing you
how to run the program
with different inputs and do you get the
right outputs and so
i think those are the things that i
really hope people will take away
is is how do you write reproducible
documented really kind programs like i
really stress
that it's our program's responsibility
to show how they are intended to be used
and if you're using a module in python
like arg parse
where you describe the arguments to your
program it can do all this
data validation for you and also present
the user a usage statement like here's
how i intended to be used and i was
one of the other projects i was working
on this over the last few months
entirely written in r and not a single
program
out of dozens and dozens of programs
command line programs not a single one
uses a standard module in r for parsing
command line arguments
every single program did it manually and
so one of the first things i did was i
was like
you know there's this really nice module
over here called opt parse
and you can describe all the inputs to
your programming you can validate them
and you can you know you really erase a
lot of bugs
in this code base if you just simply
validated your arguments
first and then tried to use them later
in the program
and it was uh it was no one was really
ready to hear that yet
so i i hope that i'm teaching by
teaching vanilla python by teaching
testing ideas i'm teaching more
universal ideas that you could apply to
any language
yes so what your hope is that the things
that people take away from the book
if they later go on to do r or java or
plural or whatever other programming
language that some of the
like some of the discipline that you
showed them in testing
transfers to other programming languages
and other contexts
as well yes great so i think that's a
great way to close it
is there anything we missed on the show
anything you still want to share
with the audience no i i i'm looking
over my notes and
i i i guess there is one thing i would
say in closing and and and i
i was uh just having an exit interview
with uh so today was my very first day
at the critical path institute so on
friday i was having an exit interview
with one of my
my pis principal investigator at the
university
and and i was trying to explain why i
think
like what is the good and bad about
using python because he's pretty much
settled on that for
the project that he's working in and i
said you know there's just this inherent
complexity
involved in writing software and
python is is great in one way because
um it kind of hides a lot of that
complexity it just kind of
you don't really have to think about how
a string or an integer is represented in
memory
um you just you just create a variable
and if you put it in quotes it's a
string and python takes care of all that
and that's cool and but there comes a
point at which
programs become more and more complex
just as they start dealing with more
real world uh concerns like you you
tried to
to get some data from uh from an api
from some sort of web resource and it
failed
and the way that it fails can just cause
the whole program to just explode
i can create an exception and the
exception isn't handled then you get a
stack trace
and you know you don't necessarily want
your users to see that
and so i was trying to say that look
there is complexity
it's just that python pushes the
complexity onto the programmer to handle
and other other languages like say rust
force you
as you're writing the code to deal with
the complexity then and there
uh and the program won't even compile
until you've taken account
what happens when we try to make this
web api call
and it fails what are you going to do
you're not allowed to just disregard
well you are allowed to disregard it if
you really want to but you're making it
explicit in the code
and so i think that we should definitely
at some point really stress uh
especially to beginners that
without if you're going to work in a
language like python at some point your
programs will become
very very complex quite long and without
uh things like tests in place you're
really kind of flying by the seat of
your pants
and and so you need to understand that
there there is this complexity you
are going to have to deal with it and uh
yeah i guess that's what i would close
with
great so we will definitely add a link
to your book
uh so that people can check it out if
they're interested and we also link to
raplets the
web based browser browser-based
ide for novices are there any other
things you want to link to is there any
anywhere we can read more about the work
that you do personally or the institute
you just started working for
well the critical path institute is a
non-profit that's uh
you can find it at cpath.org i'm really
very interested to see what i'm going to
be doing i'm vaguely aware that i'm
going to be working in like
cleaning data sets and trying to find
novel uses for existing drugs and maybe
creating new drugs
and so if you're interested in that you
can find it at cdashpath.org
my website is kyclark.um but you know as
is typical i rarely update it
you know i tweet every now and then no i
i would say um
we've covered everything thank you so
much i really appreciate your time
great thanks for being on the show today
ken thank you
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin facebook twitter
or through our slack channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening